<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[The History of Research into the Effects of the Osteopathic Lesion]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[The History of Research into the Effects of the Osteopathic Lesion]]></description>
        <link>https://thegrid.ai/osteopathichistory/</link>
        <generator>The Grid</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2018 10:36:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://thegrid.ai/osteopathichistory/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2018 10:35:58 GMT</pubDate>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Andrew Taylor Still]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><strong>A review of the osteopathic lesion in relation to disease</strong></p>,<img src="https://the-grid-user-content.s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/44025fb0-89a2-4356-922c-81f6b3ea95f6.jpg" title="Andrew Taylor Still">,<p>Osteopathy, is a principle led system of healthcare. It is based on a different “paradigm” or understanding of health and unhealth, being that the organism’s most basic urge is survival and how our body is doing the best it can with the available resources and in its current environment.</p>,<p>Osteopathic pathology, is about context and understanding the adaptations that have been made because of the context. This moves us away from a tissue causing symptoms diagnosis, to a more aetiology based diagnosis.</p>,<p>We have to assess what is stopping the patient getting better, look at their internal and external environments and change what we can, which allows for nature to provide recovery as attempts to return to homeostasis are made. This is like an audit.</p>,<p>To be able to treat more than musculoskeletal problems it is important for us as osteopaths to understand the manifestations of physiological processes within a more global environment which are either observable to us (i.e. rashes) or reported to us by the patient.</p>,<img src="https://the-grid-user-content.s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/8087c880-bd5d-4f25-8e4f-596347b1886f.jpg" title="An Osteopath using an early McManus treatment table">,<p>Thus a symptom is not something going wrong but an adaptation where the autonomic system is trying to achieve something and we become aware of it because something either hurts, is uncomfortable or it doesn’t seem to function in the way we are used to.</p>,<p><strong>Principles</strong></p>,<p>One of the principles in osteopathy is the that structure and function are related and this affects the adaptive process of disease. Probably the most contentious aspect of this over the last 125 odd years has been the "osteopathic spinal lesion."</p>,<p>Osteopaths look at the structure and relate that to what is happening to the physiology. One of the factors in our relation between health and disease is the affect of the osteopathic lesion.</p>,<img src="https://the-grid-user-content.s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/1e366b2e-0016-4d64-be03-3dacb92daa5d.jpg" title="John Martin Littlejohn ">,<p>The job of the osteopath is to remove obstruction’s to healing, and this is what Littlejohn called;</p>,<p>“<em>adjustment</em>”</p>,<p>The adjustment removes the obstruction to healing and allows the healing process to begin, this sometimes creates a “reaction.”</p>,<p>In his book "Philosophy and Mechanical Principles of Osteopathy" AT Still’s first mention of something that causes a disturbance to circulation is on p. 10</p>,<p>"<em>I began to realise the power of nature to cure after skilful correction of conditions and abnormalities had been accomplished so to bring forth pure and healthy blood, the greatest known germicide.</em>"</p>,<p>So healthy blood is important, without healthy blood the internal secretions cannot be made correctly as each gland that secretes its specialist substance is made from blood. Blood distributes the ingredients and these specialist structures take what is needed.</p>,<p>So we need to consume what the blood needs to have the correct ingredients within it to keep us healthy, but we also need to be able to digest it and thus we need the vasomotor system to be functioning correctly to open the gates for blood to pass into the mesenteric system.</p>,<p>Modern evidence (for example from Dr Dean Ornish) would suggest than plant based diets incorporating raw foods are really helpful in reducing inflammation and assist in helping our bodies eliminate waste from the cellular space.</p>,<p>Here he is discussing how nature always endeavours to make the organism survive and restoring circulation to tissue which has undergone adaptive change will allow this adaptive compensation, commonly known as “disease” to become unnecessary.</p>,<p>His adjustment of what he considers abnormal changes to the structure which effects the physiology, living organisms strive to survive, this is nature. Thus Still observed that improving the circulation to an area helped nature restore tissue to a healthier condition.</p>,<p>It’s interesting that he mentions germicide and his book is from 1910, when germ theory had gained acceptance as the cause of diseases by medicine.</p>,<p>We are looking to help nature do its bit and repair our patients, to do this we have to look at everything in their environment which may be affecting their health and change what we can.</p>,<p>Still on p. 36 of Philosophy of Osteopathy mentions how lesions of the 11th and 12th ribs prolapse the diaphragm affecting circulation through the vena cava at the level of the 4th lumbar.</p>,<p>"<em>Then you have cause for an intermittent pulse, as the heart finds no passage of blood through the prolapse diaphragm which is also stopping the vena cava, producing universal stagnation of blood and other fluids in all organs and glands below the diaphragm. From this, you have the beginning for abnormal growths of the womb, kidneys and all lymphatics of the liver, kidneys spleen and pancreas,and all tumours of the abdomen</em>."</p>,<p>These are Still’s thoughts on the aetiology of certain pathological processes.</p>,<p>On p39 he refers to slipped or twisted vertebra, not specifically mentioning "lesion." Further on in the paragraph Still states "I contend that the curing comes direct from the liberation of the interspinal and intercostal nerves, freed of the bone pressure on the nerves of motion, sensation and nutrition. Did Still not like the word lesion?</p>,<p>This is Still suggesting or stating that stagnation and congestion alters the physiology and the tissues adapt to the situation.</p>,<p>The earliest recollected research started in March 1898, Dr. Goetz and Littlejohn were regularly working together in the evenings to compile Littlejohn’s physiology notes into the book “Physiology Exhaustive and Practical” and the subject of research was discussed, from here another discussion took place involving JML and Goetz and CMT Hulett, the trio decided to take the idea to Charlie Still and AT Still.</p>,<p>During the winter of 1898-99 experiments were conducted on animals in an old barn on Osteopathy Avenue, Kirksville and at the ASO on human subjects and dogs with regard to the effects of stimulation and inhibition and the effects of lesions produced and their attempted correction. JM Littlejohn recorded a number of spygmograghs and cardiographs during that year and sectioned the heart, lung and spinal cord of dogs subjected to experiments under anaesthesia.</p>,<p>JM Littlejohn and AT Still dissected out the entire spinal cord, made sections of the brain, and watched the peristalsis and rhythm of the internal organs.</p>,<p>At the suggestion of AT Still, JM Littlejohn experimented on the use of morphine, quinine, iron and arsenic administered to animals, with the object of proving, as JM Littlejohn attempted to demonstrate that these substances were foreign to the body and produced detrimental instead of beneficial effects. AT Still also was the first to suggest a series of experiments that JM Littlejohn performed at his home in South Main Street which was to demonstrate the the capacity of the organism to flush the lungs in case of pneumonia.</p>,<p>When strychnine was applied to local disturbances, without fail it led to organic pathology in the animal and this appeared to be organised via the spinal cord.</p>,<p>JM Littlejohn also witnessed AT Still experimenting out behind his own old home on the ability of the organism to make its own water supply and on the relation of the lymphatic system to obesity.</p>,<p>In the literature of the late 1800's these disturbances where being less frequently described as dislocations as a description of a gross deviation in palpable anatomy and a partial dislocation or a minor subluxation for what would appear as a lesser degree of anatomical disturbance and the term “lesion” starts to become mentioned and was often categorised as being either osseous, muscular or ligamentous, visceral and composite.</p>,<img src="https://the-grid-user-content.s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/fb41ab04-d366-4c8d-8384-2ce5543ca4a5.jpg" title="Kirksville 1898, South West Quarter">,<p>Map of Kirksville’s south west quarter in 1898 showing several residences.</p>,<img src="https://the-grid-user-content.s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/5d347c49-5949-49b9-9720-e6ade9ea750f.jpg">,<p>Chart of 1240 cases that presented at Washington Institute of Osteopathy, only 3% were for lumbago.</p>,<p><strong>Carl P McConnell DO</strong></p>,<img src="https://the-grid-user-content.s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/be6c983e-b471-4eef-afa4-82ffd5e639b3.jpg">,<p>McConnell was an early osteopathic researcher.</p>,<p>In 1905 Carl P McConnell DO, reported the findings of his research at the AOA meeting in Denver, this work was in the physiology laboratories at the Pacific College of Osteopathy. Experiments were undertaken initially on 6 dogs. With an assistant, dogs were “lesioned” under anaesthesia. There was no direct tissue damage, and the dogs were observed from 3-80 days after lesioning before an autopsy was performed were samples were collected.</p>,<p>In 1905 he presented some of the results performed under the auspices of the AT Still Research Institute from a series of animal experiments on dogs at the AOA meetings in Denver and San Francisco.</p>,<p>The dogs, which were due to undergo experimental lesioning were anaesthetised and a lesion was produced by traction, extension and rotation. This was not performed so there was any direct tissue damage, the object was to achieve what was described as a “slight slipping” or maladjustment of the articular surfaces. The dogs were observed for a period of 3 to 80 days from lesion production to autopsy.</p>,<p>Before the lesion was dissected a thorough autopsy was performed and specimens secured of various organs and tissues whether or not they showed any pathological changes or were directly neurologically related to the lesioned structure.</p>,<p>Great care was taken during dissection, the spinal cord levels are removed with the ribs, local muscles and other tissues.</p>,<p>The lesion: effect at the foramina or due to something else?</p>,<p>The foramina involved in the lesions were examined and they failed to see any signs of occlusion and thus concluded that this, as a cause of the effects of the lesion were untenable.</p>,<p>He noted that muscular tension alone seemed to not produce a permanent lesion, complete removal of the muscles in the area of the lesion failed to change the vertebral rigidity of the lesion (as you may recall at this time lesions were often classified as osseous, muscular or ligamentous, visceral and composite). Removal of the ribs made little difference. It was found that the permanent vertebral lesion was maintained by overstretched and damaged articular ligaments, once these were cut the segments motion was restored.</p>,<p><strong>Microscopic Examination</strong></p>,<p>At the level of the lesion structures of the cord, nerve roots and their branches and the sympathetics corresponding to the lesion were pathologically damaged. The tissues of the controls showed no such changes.</p>,<p>Various cell groups in the grey matter showed inflammatory changes and atrophy.</p>,<p>Axon degeneration extended above and below the lesion.</p>,<p>Degeneration was traced from the nerve centres in the cord, posterior root ganglion and sympathetics. Usually between a third and two thirds of the bundle were affected.</p>,<p>Mainly affected were the vasomotors.</p>,<p>These were deranged from the endothelial cells through the muscle fibres and the outer layer into the surrounding tissue.</p>,<p>In the surrounding tissues variable quantities of blood corpuscles were found enmeshed, from the escape of blood plasma and leucocytes via diapedesis and haemorrhage demonstrating evidence of local adaptive or pathological change. Again however McConnell and his researchers speculated that the changes would not be unable to repair if the environment was amenable.</p>,<p>Changes in blood vessels were observed to the outer adventitia of the arterioles, capillaries, veins and sometimes arteries.</p>,<p>Diapedesis and haemorrhage was evidence of local pathological change.</p>,<p>Hyperaemic arteritis due to the local vasomotor changes extending above and below the segment involved.</p>,<p>Marked disturbances to the blood vessels of the sympathetics, this vasomotor effect frequently extended to the neurologically related viscera.</p>,<p>Pronounced hyperaemia of the cord, especially but not exclusively in the posterior horns and medial sides of the anterior horns. Ischaemia was greatest at the level of the lesion.</p>,<p>Congestion with diapedesis was noted in the anterior and posterior spinal cord vessels.</p>,<p>In a number of the smaller arteries a well defined hyperaemic arteritis was observed, due to local vasomotor changes.</p>,<p>These changes were not only confined to the level of the lesion but also extended above and below the segment involved to a reduced degree, becoming less the further away the segment was from the lesion. The disturbances to the blood vessels of the sympathetics seemed well marked.</p>,<p>Circulatory changes to neurologically related viscera were frequently detected due to the effected vasomotors.</p>,<p>The hyperaemia of the cord was pronounced, especially in the grey matter, throughout the posterior horns and the tips and medial sides of the anterior horns were the areas most disturbed (sensory and motor nuclei nerve centres), but the disturbance was not exclusive to these areas.</p>,<p>Circulatory changes varied in different cell groups, the ischaemia was greatest at the level of the lesion and gradually lessens by segment or two above or below the lesion. Congestion with diapedesis of the anterior and posterior spinal cord vessels was readily noted.</p>,<p>McConnell's theoretical conclusion from his microscopic examination that the damage caused a “blockage” of the afferent sensory impulses of the joint structure and surrounding tissues followed by reflex segmental disturbance to the efferent vasomotor, motor and other fibres.</p>,<p>At the same time normal tissues were run through the same testing procedures as a control, these all appeared normal.</p>,<p>The lesioned areas showed acute pathological disturbances and not antemortem changes or artefacts.</p>,<p>The microscopic changes in the muscle were clear and well defined, the contracture was due to an interstitial myositis, with an easily seen increase of connective tissue and atrophy of the muscle fibres. The nerve to these fibres was found to be degenerated, as well as the related arterioles and veins.</p>,<p><strong>Visceral Effects</strong></p>,<p>Diapedesis and vessel congestion in the sub mucous coat of the stomach and intestines.</p>,<p>Secretory, motor and digestive powers were altered and reduced.</p>,<p>Kidney disturbances of a vascular nature, changes by way of the vasomotors, congestion and a typical haemorrhagic infiltration.</p>,<p>Liver and spleen congestion.</p>,<p>Pancreatic damage (acutely disordered), considerable congestion of the islets of Langerhans (three days post lesion urinalysis showed raised glucose).</p>,<p>The lesion effects upon the viscera corresponded to the innervation.</p>,<p>It appeared that impairment of the vasomotors plays the important role, although undoubtedly the visceromotor, secretory and other nerve fibres are a factor also, these are often a secondary effect of a vasomotor problem.</p>,<p>Congestion and inflammation are basic to the large majority of diseases and in all the experiments they found vessel disturbance a constant feature, whether in the immediate locality of the lesion or as a remote effect.</p>,<p>Observed effects in stomach and intestines;</p>,<p>- reduced secretory, motor function.</p>,<p>- vessel congestion in the sub-mucous coat, usually accompanied by diapedesis.</p>,<p>- in some severe cases the cells of the mucous coat are nutritionally involved with areas of feeble staining, parenchymatous and accompanying pathological changes.</p>,<p>The kidney changes were interesting and had taken place when the lesion was produced at the 11th, 12th and 13th dorsals only. It appeared that the vasomotors were effected. The disturbance is a vascular one, resulting in congestion and typical haemorrhagic infiltration.</p>,<p><strong>Other visceral disturbances occurred;</strong></p>,<p>in a number the liver and spleen were found congested, the liver</p>,<p>especially in the middle lobe and the cellular tissue was nutritionally effected.</p>,<p>in two cases the pancreas was found to be acutely disordered, with</p>,<p>considerable congestion throughout several of the islets of Langerhans and urinalysis after the third day showed a moderate amount of sugar.</p>,<p>The adrenals in one case that was lesioned at the lower dorsals showed congestion.</p>,<p>A parenchymatous goiter formed in two of the animals, one of the these had a lesion between the second and third cervical, the other between the second and third dorsal, in both there was a local lymphadenopathy.</p>,<p>The time period between death of the animal and the tissue being placed in fixing fluid was only a few minutes.</p>,<p><strong>McConnell's Conclusions;</strong></p>,<p>1. The osteopathic lesion is something more than an effect at the foramen.</p>,<p>2. Initially, there is physiological disturbance of the muscular, fascial, ligamentous and osseous tissues which causes interference with normal afferention to the spinal cord centres and this is more or less permanently maintained by the lack of freedom of the normal joint movements.</p>,<p>3. This initiates the associated changes in the spinal cord segment.</p>,<p>4. This interference to the constant afferent feed back system must disturb functioning and as a consequence the vasomotor and other centres are affected.</p>,<p>5. Vessel dilation and congestion is a prominent feature.</p>,<p>6. The arterioles, capillaries and veins are pathologically affected by the disturbed innervation.</p>,<p>7. The blood stream is slowed, the endothelial tissue compromised and plasma exudation takes place. This is followed by diapedesis leading to small areas of haemorrhage, especially in and about the nerve centres of the cord and ganglia, thus nutrition of local parts is jeopardised and causes parenchymatous degeneration.</p>,<p>In the large majority of cases only a portion of cord cells are affected and likewise the axons.</p>,<p>Certain paths are more affected than others and the entire neuron suffers thus pointing to a central cause with a corresponding disturbance to the subsidiary and collateral neurones. This accounts for the pathologic changes in nearby segments and ganglia and of course the related viscera.</p>,<p>8. Many lesions if not all effect the health of the tissues and organs innervated and related to them, therefore acting as an etiological, predisposing or maintaining factor to disease process’s. This relates to the phrase "every lesion is a vital lesion" and would be a factor in reducing the individuals natural resistance.</p>,<p>10. Nervous tissue, especially the ganglia from the cord to the sympathetics and the connective tissue are richly supplied with blood, osteopathically the greatest disturbance seems to be in these nerve centres. Owing to the sensitivity of nerve cells to circulatory changes it’s a small step from functional impairment to organic disorder.</p>,<p><strong>Louisa Burns DO</strong></p>,<p>Louisa Burns is a much maligned and discredited early osteopathic researcher and pioneer. Most that discredit her work have never looked at it, do not know what it is and how relevant it still is today. For the first part of the 20th century she was the dominant figure in osteopathic research.</p>,<p>Her life’s work was dedicated to studying the pathological changes associated with and following osteopathic lesions.</p>,<p>Whereas McConnell put a lot of focus on the local affects of the lesion Burns research focused on body wide affects.</p>,<p>Experiments were mainly performed on small mammals such as white rats, rabbits, guinea pigs and some cats.</p>,<p>Her research was funded by the profession and by herself.</p>,<p>Don’t ask her to look after your pet.</p>,<p>Louisa Burns DO (1868-1958) graduated as an osteopath in 1903 and later completed a Masters degree in science. She came to osteopathy after suffering long term effects from meningitis and was helped greatly back to nearly full health by an osteopath her parents took her to in California.</p>,<p>For the first half of the 20th century she was the dominant figure in osteopathic research.</p>,<p>She had a wide area of interest and was a prolific writer.</p>,<p>Her life's work was studying the pathological changes associated with and following osteopathic lesions.</p>,<p>The work was initially funded by the profession via the AT Still Research Institute. Funding from the Institute disappeared in the 1930's from then on she funded it herself.</p>,<p>Experiments were mainly performed on rabbits, guinea pigs, white rats and some cats.</p>,<p>Lesions were experimentally induced, and always correlated to clinical observation to add practical value.</p>,<p>The quality of Burns work has been much maligned, questioned and criticised perhaps in part as she was an "osteopathic researcher." Gevitz, in his 1982 book "The DO's" does an acute hatchet job by inventing abuse by misquoting his sources. My experience of this has been that most people who criticise her work have nor read it and hve been told that it is poor quality from people who also haven’t spent the time to study it.</p>,<p>George Cole DO wrote</p>,<p>"Her work has been criticised often without justification when it has been taken out of its historical context.</p>,<p>She has been faulted for lack of proper control, although she was adamant in maintaining proper control.</p>,<p>She has been criticised for using non scientific methods when she was contributing to the development of those methods.</p>,<p>She was called repetitious, but today repetition is considered necessary for substantiation of a theory by experimental methods."</p>,<p>Some of her work can be faulted for lack of proper referencing, however much of her work was original.</p>,<p>Or perhaps that initial funding was from the osteopathic profession.</p>,<p>In the 1935 Osteopathic Bill, Kelman MacDonald MD, DO, could only criticise her research for not being performed in a world renowned laboratory.</p>,<p>Norman Allan PhD stated "Burns has too much to offer for us to just ignore her and consider her primitive or eccentric." (The Journal of the CCA / vol 30 No.2 June 1986)</p>,<p>Adaptive Effects of Bony lesions</p>,<p>(extracted from Research Institute Bulletin No. 4, "The Pathology of the Vertebral Lesion" 1917)</p>,<p>Due to her years of research, Burns placed it as a fact that these lesions cause disturbed circulation, disturbed function and lowered immunity, this had been demonstrated by clinical evidence which appeared to be conclusive and also by laboratory experiments on animals.</p>,<p>Burns summarised the adaptation of physiology caused by the osteopathic lesion;</p>,<p>1. Direct pressure effects. Changes in boney relations, abnormal relationship of articular surfaces, sensory effects of including inflammation, stress and strain of ligaments.</p>,<p>2. Effects of sensory irritation. Disturbances acting on the sensory side within the spinal cord provide the basis of how the lesion acts on visceral centres modifying visceral function.</p>,<p>The lesion has 2 distinct injuries;</p>,<p>The lesion itself sends aberrant information into the cord,</p>,<p>Diminished mobility prevents the normal sensory impulses from being produced.</p>,<p>These unequal factors cause the varying effects of the lesion sometimes visceral effects being increased, sometimes diminished and sometimes variable.</p>,<p>3. Effects of muscular tension. Reflex muscular contraction due to sensory disturbance, haemorrhagic areas occur in these muscles.</p>,<p>4. Effects of ligamentous changes. Sensory information from ligaments around the lesion leads to afferent bombardment of the cord affecting the function of the viscera and other spinal centres. This has been experimentally demonstrated in animals.</p>,<p>The long continued slight pressure due to the osteopathic lesion is much more disturbing in its nerve reflexes than sudden trauma.</p>,<p>5. Effects of local oedema. In 1917 it was a recent discovery that localised oedema caused a drop in pH leading to acidosis. Several days after the lesion has been present, connective tissue growth is formed around the area causing a slight thickening of the surrounding connective tissue.</p>,<p>6. Effects of local haemorrhages. These occur via diapedesis. With vertebral lesions these seemed to form in three areas;</p>,<p>Over the tips of the spinous process’s.</p>,<p>In the subcutaneous connective tissues along the spinal column at the outer limits of the transverse process’s.</p>,<p>In the deep layers of the muscle near the spinal column.</p>,<p>Not only in the local tissues do the haemorrhages occur, but they are also present in the organs innervated by the lesioned level again this was an effect of diapedesis.</p>,<p>7. Effects of localised acidosis. These are different depending on the structure involved, the non medullated nerve fibres of the visceral and vascular systems appear to be more severely effected than the medullated fibres.</p>,<p>Slide 22</p>,<p>General effects of the lesion on body tissues;</p>,<p>Circulatory disturbances. In general an ischaemic response was noted. All studies thus far had indicated that circulatory disturbances cause disease. From the earliest days of osteopathy this has been noted, Dr. Still's earliest writings are full of this relationship and that the minute of the hour that the circulation is impeded marks the start of disease. All studies thus far had indicated that circulatory disturbance initiates disease.</p>,<p>2. Viscero motor effects. Effects noted in Bulletin No. 5, changes in digestive tract motility in animal experiments, variation in heart action in animals or humans experimentally lesioned in areas that affect the cardiac centres measured before and after lesion correction. Variation in the time required for complete emptying of the stomach in persons before and after correction of lesions indicates the importance of the lesion as a aetiological factor in gastric dilation.</p>,<p>3. Vertebral effects of lesions. The effects of vertebral lesions on the spinal column itself had received little attention. The lesion limits motion, promotes connective tissue overgrowth, produces circulatory disturbances in the surrounding tissue, is associated with oedema and acidosis and has an adverse effect on the stream of both afferent and efferent impulses. Limited motion affects factors that promote the flow of blood and lymph and thus the flow is reduced.</p>,<p>Sensory and mental effects of lesions.</p>,<p>Lesions of the cervical and upper dorsal spine may affect the circulation through the brain, this is known to occur in animals where the meninges are quite obviously effected.</p>,<p>Burns wrote in her 1921 paper "Somato Sensory Impulses" that "Sensory impulses acting through the cortical neurons are subject to judgement and reason, again, being a result of a co-ordination of past experiences of the individual and of other individuals with whom he/she has been associated."</p>,<p>This statement written in 1921, displays knowledge of ascending influences being affected by the hypothalamus and limbic systems and their effects on descending impulses influenced by past experience and emotion.</p>,<p>Slide 23</p>,<p>Extracted from Research Institute Bulletin No. 4, "The Pathology of the Vertebral Lesion" 1917</p>,<p>Due to her years of research, Burns placed it as a fact that these lesions cause disturbed circulation, disturbed function and lowered immunity, this had been demonstrated by clinical evidence which appeared to be conclusive and also by laboratory experiments on animals.</p>,<p>For 50 years Louisa Burns studied the effects of osteopathic spinal lesions on tissue and with very few exceptions there was a single consistent response in all tissues, and this was an ischaemic response. This she was confident in stating is the missing link between health and disease.</p>,<p>Slide 24</p>,<p>End of Louisa Burns</p>,<p>Slide 25</p>,<p>Slide 26</p>,<p>Slide 21</p>,<p>John Stedman Denslow DO</p>,<p>John Stedman Denslow DO was the husband of AT Stills grand daughter, he also worked at the Sunny Slopes Laboratory under Louisa Burns and was the first to objectively measure the presence of a lesion and publish his results in a peer review journal. His research was legitimised as it had National Institute of Health funding, in part, this was secured by removing the word “osteopathy” from the name of the laboratory as it was considered too contentious.</p>,<p>So the laboratory at KCOM was renamed the Still Memorial Research Trust until enough quality research had been published to use the word osteopathy.</p>,<p>He developed a pressure meter that could excerpt 1-7 kg of pressure, this was used over lesioned and non lesioned areas and the reflex contractions were measured by EMG.</p>,<p>The result of which demonstrated the lesioned segments produced a reflex contraction or action potential EMG reading at a much lower pressure than the non lesioned segments. The non lesioned segments often produced no response at all on the EMG with up to 7kg pressure. This led to the concept of the facilitated segment and was the first objective evidence of the physiological affects of the osteopathic lesion.</p>,<p>Denslow’s early work which was published in the Journal of Neurophysiology can be summarised;</p>,<p>Rigid muscles (lesioned areas) associated with postural anomalies commonly show spontaneous action potentials.</p>,<p>When such spontaneous activity is absent, it can be induced by suitable stimuli; this is a useful criterion for detecting lesion areas.</p>,<p>Induced reflex activity is probably dependent on the presence of enduring central excitatory state or facilitation plus an accessory subliminal stimulus.</p>,<p>Denslow was the first DO to put research related to osteopathy into the scientific sphere and into scientific journals.</p>,<p>One of the key differences between the earlier research by Burn’s and McConnell and the research by Denslow was the financial pathway it took to funding.</p>,<p>Slide 28</p>,<p>Irvin Korr PhD (1909 - 2004)</p>,<p>After post graduate studies in physiology at Princeton University Irvin Korr established himself as a well known scholar in various areas of physiology. He was interested in the work of Denslow and his associates and joined Kirksville College of Osteopathy and Surgery in 1945 as professor and chairman of the physiology department.</p>,<p>From here he started to explore the biologic foundations of the principles of osteopathy.</p>,<p>Together Korr and Denslow spent decades adding scientific legitimacy, through experimentation and publication, to the empirical evidence we observe in clinical practice.</p>,<p>Much of their early work centred on demonstrating the arousal of the sympathetic nervous system associated with the osteopathic lesion.</p>,<p>Korr offered interpretations of Denlow’s research findings in terms of neural function and the concept of the facilitated segment was developed as an underpinning of the osteopathic lesion.</p>,<p>Korr’s first paper at Kirksville followed on from Denslow’s work contrasting the EMG study findings with palpatory examination findings. This extended the results to provide clear definitions of the characteristics of changes in skeletal muscle activity associated with osteopathic lesions. He also speculated on possible causes and maintaining influences for the objectively observed activity.</p>,<p>The second paper was one of Korr’s most important works in the osteopathic profession, “The neural basis of the osteopathic lesion,” where he put forward the idea of the “neurologic lens” and the “facilitated segment.”</p>,<p>This major theory of regional excitation of the spinal cord and areas of increased activity being caused by both external and internal sources of stimulation. The focus of this activity being in areas of adaptive patterns of skeletal, visceral and glandular activity was a conceptual breakthrough.</p>,<p>He presented his paper The Neural Basis Osteopathic Lesion tentatively at the AOA convention in 1947.</p>,<p>As a result osteopaths began to contemplate the concepts of afferent bombardment of the central nervous system, facilitation, the role of the cerebral cortex, postural equilibrium centres, bulbar centres, cutaneous receptors and others that can maintain a hyper irritability state of the CNS.</p>,<p>I’m not sure how many of these US osteopaths would have been aware of Littlejohn’s assertion that “all disease starts on the sensory side.”</p>,<p>From these first papers flowed research over the next 17 years from 1948 to 1965. The major impact was to demonstrate the existence of increased patterns of activity in the autonomic nervous system in apparently healthy as well as unhealthy people and the correlation of some adaptive hyper irritable autonomic patterns with musculoskeletal changes.</p>,<p>Korr’s keen interest in the neurophysiology led to the gamma loop hypothesis for the persistence of increased muscle tone associated with the osteopathic lesion (1975). This train of thought was adopted by Fred Mitchell, and also Laurence Jones, to legitimise the theories of Muscle Energy and Strain Counter strain techniques respectively.</p>,<p>Korr passionately demonstrated that the glorification of the viscera and medical specialism was a mistake in attempting to understand the human organism. As these structures play a supporting role to musculoskeletal system which he called “the primary machinery of life.”</p>,<p>The visceral, autonomic and endocrine systems, through their action in and on the internal environment have logistical and maintenance roles that enable the primary machinery to function by making the necessary adjustments demanded. The autonomic nervous system has a major role in making the adjustments necessary to visceral, circulatory and metabolic activity according to the demand of the primary machinery.</p>,<p>He enjoyed pointing out that the common diagrams of the sympathetic nervous system which show multitudes of fibres passing to the viscera with the musculoskeletal system being shown as having a few scant connections was the wrong way round as the musculoskeletal system had 90% of the total connections with the nervous system.</p>,<p>Korr was terribly disappointed in the late 1950’s when the osteopathic profession decided to go against his lobbying and align itself with medicine in the US.</p>,<p>He wrote a landmark papers about the role of the spinal cord as an organiser of disease and the role of the sympathetic nervous system as a factor in disease. These insights in 1979 were visionary as by 1992 Bellinger and Felton et al. had demonstrated that nearly all tissues of the body are innervated by fibres from the sympathetic nervous system rather than just pylo erectors of hair follicles, sweat glands and blood vessels as depicted in traditional neuroanatomy texts.</p>,<p>Unfortunately this is still not appreciated today in the same way that the raising of sympathetic tone being a factor in disease in not appreciated, most likely due to medical specialism.</p>,<p>Korr’s later work involved the investigation into transport of substances through axons to end tissues. These substances are released from the cell body and the health of the end tissue is dependent upon them. Additionally substances travel back from the end tissue to the cell body. Varying speeds of axoplasmic flow where recorded travelling the length of the axon in either hours to several months.</p>,<p>Korr was a prolific scientific researcher, philosopher and advocate of osteopathy.</p>,<p>Slide 29</p>,<p>Korr’s experiments</p>,<p>Fig 1, is an example of a case showing a number of areas lesioned when examined originally by Denslow.</p>,<p>Fig 2, shows the electrical skin resistance, the dark areas correspond to areas of low resistance which is approximately 5% of the white areas resistance.</p>,<p>Fig 3, shows the vascular response the thin lines being the areas of vasoconstriction and the thick lines vasodilation.</p>,<p>Fig 4, shows an EMG of the spinal extensors whilst standing relaxed.</p>,<p>These areas of lowered resistance where persistent, sometimes for years.</p>,<p>Many otherwise healthy subjects had sensitised or lowered areas of resistance, it became evident that subject to subject variability and from further data which showed that the excitability increases often accompanied injury and disease, and were not the “normal” state.</p>,<p>These were areas “out of synchrony” with other areas of the nervous system, causing the viscera supplied by those nervous structures to be “out of synchrony” with the total body function, or a part of the body which is not responding to the variability of the requirements of homeostatic mechanisms in the organism.</p>,<p>Further studies demonstrated that the areas of low resistance represented facilitated areas of the sympathetic nervous system.</p>,<p>And, evidence was demonstrated that the cutaneous vasculature in the areas resistant to dilatation was maintained in a state of exaggerated vasomotor tone or vasoconstriction.</p>,<p>These aberrant areas differed physiologically from adjacent or normal areas and responded to stress in an impaired, limited or exaggerated manner.</p>,<p>Summary of Findings</p>,<p>It would appear from the studies presented of sensory, motor and autonomic activity studied on the surface of the body, that;</p>,<p>Aberrant segments of the spinal cord occur in most individuals, including apparently healthy persons.</p>,<p>These segments are abnormal in their tonic activity and in their response to various stimuli.</p>,<p>In these segments at least some of the neurons mediating motor, sensory and autonomic function are maintained in a state of hyperactivity, manifested by their easier, increased and prolonged responses to impulses reaching them from many sources.</p>,<p>They are therefore susceptible to sustained and exaggerated activity under conditions of daily life.</p>,<p>The influence normally exerted by these neurons on tissues may thereby be exaggerated.</p>,<p>These segmental disturbances appear to be physiologic lesions related, by nature and location, to the clinical phenomena designated as osteopathic lesions. In other words the osteopathic lesion is a physiological lesion not an anatomical phenomena.</p>,<p>Significance of cutaneous signs of local sympatheticotonia;</p>,<p>As previously stated, prominent areas of low electrical skin resistance are often found in dermatomes segmentally related to pathological viscera. Hyperhydrosis in dermatomes related to pathologic viscera has also been demonstrated by other researchers.</p>,<p>In a significant percentage of apparently healthy subjects, there were prominent areas of low electrical skin resistance in which overt disease later appeared or which were especially susceptible to symptoms of a disturbance under stressful conditions.</p>,<p>Clinical reports have previously appeared in the literature about many serious clinical entities that are associated with autonomic imbalance of sympatheticotonia.</p>,<p>(See Raised Sympatheticotonia as a Factor in Disease).</p>,<p>A number of visceral and other chronic diseases appear to begin as ischaemic states of the involved tissues (see Burns and McConnell) due to local neurogenic vasospasm. This vasospasm seems to be of local sympathetic origin and is also associated with vasospasm in related segments of skin. This directly correlates to Louisa Burns work.</p>,<p>It appeared well established by Korr’s work that the vasomotor responses in the skin and in the viscera are quite parallel. Stimuli that causes vasoconstriction in one, commonly also does so in the other. This is the pattern associated with diffuse sympathetic activation, for example, in muscular effort and in certain responses to intense environmental or emotional stimulation, when blood is shunted from viscera and skin to the skeletal muscles.</p>,<p>It also appeared certain that this facilitation of local sympathetic pathways is not just a local cutaneous disturbance but is commonly part of a generalised sympathetic hyper-irritability affecting other tissues innervated from related parts of the nervous system.</p>,<p>Conclusions;</p>,<p>The "osteopathic lesion" as identified by palpation and various other criteria is the local or regionally discrete somatic component of a reflexly organised and sustained response to stresses, irritations and excessive demands placed upon specific tissues or organs by the environment and by the total activities, responses and adaptations of the individual. It is a physiological adaptation to maintain movement.</p>,<p>It’s the tip of an iceberg. The lesioned segment acts as a neurologic lens due to the sustained facilitation of sensory, motor and autonomic pathways, these focus and exaggerate the effects from many sources upon the tissues innervated by that segment. Through that segment the individual is subjected to the exaggerated impact of his life situations and environmental factors into the facilitated segment and the structures it supplies and therefore the organism as a whole, even ordinarily innocuous life situations become relatively stressful or taxing and may continually demand and evoke costly, reserve-reducing protective responses. It acts as a path of least resistance.</p>,<p>In addition to point 2, among the sources of impulses that create strain through facilitated segments are the higher cerebral centres. The osteopathic lesion is an unquestionably important factor in the bodily expression of emotional ills, conflicts and tension. An interesting statement, as previously mentioned by Burns the descending affect from the higher centres of the limbic system etc.</p>,<p>The local initiating stresses in man arise most frequently in the musculo-skeletal system, because of its incomplete adaptation to the bipedal posture and because of each individuals postural adaptation to gravitational factors and stresses.</p>,<p>Regardless of the mode of initiation a somatic component is reflexly established which reflexly increases and sustains the facilitatory process and sensitises every disease process to the influence of gravity.</p>,<p>The local and segmental raised sympathetic tone and neurovascular disturbances secondary to this phenomena, are being increasingly recognised as contributing to endogenous chronic diseases and appear to be a prominent part of this general process.</p>,<p>According to conclusions 2 and 3, whether or not and the degree to which disease develops through the facilitated segment, will be determined by the total demands upon the individual and by other factors such as psychological, nutritional, social, hereditary, age, etc. which influence his natural resistance. Therefore the osteopathic lesion inevitably impairs an individuals natural resistance to some extent, while the importance of the lesion to the individual is determined by their total adequacy to their total environment and to the life situations he encounters and creates. The lesion increases the importance of every stress which also renders the importance of the lesion more critical. This is what I think is meant by the phrase "every lesion is a vital lesion."</p>,<p>Since the response to local stress, irritation, or excessive demand is basically the same through the various nerve influences, the potential clinical manifestations will be determined by the segment involved and its associated tissues rather than by the nature of the insult or aetiological event itself. The same process acting through different segments and tissues, produces a variety of syndromes. The location of the lesion determines the target organs and therefore the potential diseases. Since the location of the lesions that occur in response to stress and strain of the erect posture is significantly influenced by bodily configuration, this appears to be an important factor in the relationship between body type and the incidence of various diseases. (this harks back to Goldthwaite's book "Body Mechanics in Health and Disease")</p>,<p>Therapeutic Implications;</p>,<p>Attention must be given to all the controllable factors in the patients environment which influence their body economy.</p>,<p>Because the facilitation of the lesion increases the vulnerability of the individual to all factors, critical importance should be attached to the treatment of the lesions. This is not the case, we have to drop the specific.</p>,<p>Since all the existing lesions impair the resources of the ill patient for further resistance and recovery, regardless of their apparent aetiologic relation to the illness, no therapy can be be complete without liberating these resources.</p>,<p>The direct effect of disturbing influences being exaggerated by the lesion, its accessibility and and its response to rational treatment render it an important factor through which to modify the response of the disease process and to augment the individuals response, natural resistance, recovery and adaptation.</p>,<p>JML’s adjustment</p>,<p>In conclusion, since the osteopathic lesion reflects and influences;</p>,<p>i. the adequacy of the individuals reserves and resources,</p>,<p>ii. the adequacy of their responses to the demands of life,</p>,<p>iii. their vulnerability and predisposition,</p>,<p>Early diagnosis and treatment of the osteopathic lesion offers a direct and systematic approach to the prevention of chronic disease for which, as far as we can tell, there is no substitute.</p>,<p>Slide 30</p>,<p>What is also known now but was not known by Korr was;</p>,<p>The spinal cord can become sensitised or facilitated and relay nociceptive signals to the brainstem where other reflexes concerning the ANS and endocrine system may be initiated. This does not necessarily lead to the sensation of pain. These events can occur without conscious awareness of the situation. Probably a bit like what medicine calls sub clinical.</p>,<p>These wide spread effects were viewed as a threat to health and function of the patient. An area of spinal reflex pathways are either temporarily or permanently in a state of increased excitability and respond to input or stimulation in a exaggerated way and act in a way that is out of harmony with the rest of the body. Over time this would be expected to have an effect on the functional abilities of the related tissues and could result in breakdown or loss of normal function. Integration</p>,<p>This is were the health state crosses into the un-health state.</p>,<p>A large number of visceral and other chronic diseases appear to begin as ischaemic states of the involved tissues (see Burns) due to local neurogenic vasospasm. This vasospasm seems to be of local sympathetic origin and is also associated with vasospasm in related segments of skin. This directly correlates to Louisa Burns work.</p>,<p>Michael Patterson PhD</p>,<p>Michael Patterson is a now retired osteopathic researcher in the same vein as Korr. In fact he worked under Korr.</p>,<p>Somato visceral reflexes demonstrate summation caused by the wind up phenomenon and the effects of input from different parts of the body. These somato visceral reflexes do not reach their maximal activity immediately. But when stimulated at a low repetition rate, these reflexes exhibit “wind up.” With each repetition of the stimulus up to about 20 times, the autonomic response increases in size.</p>,<p>This wind up or sensitisation phenomenon, suggests that maximum therapeutic procedure effectiveness involving somatic afferent influences on autonomic control may require frequent repetitions of the procedure to allow the response to build to its maximum. ie slow rhythmic articulation of bodily structures to effect visceral function.</p>,<p>Additionally afferent input from from different portions of the body can summate to activate autonomic responses.</p>,<p>This integrating reflex system is important to osteopaths as somatic input can and does affect visceral function just as visceral input can affect somatic structures and we palpate this as as altered tissue tensions around joints and the changes in motion characteristics etc.</p>,<p>Patterson, Wurster &amp; Janig (The Science and Clinical application of Manual Therapy 2010</p>,<p>This is well worth studying;</p>,<p>The osteopathic lesion was conceived as one of the primary factors influencing the body economy and the root of many diseases.</p>,<p>Louisa Burns and her colleagues performed many studies on the effects of lesions on visceral function, thus showing many somato-visceral influences.</p>,<p>While previously thought of as hard wired pathways, reflexes are complex interconnections influenced by many factors such as ascending/descending messages and general excitability of the CNS.</p>,<p>Somato-visceral and viscero-somatic reflexes are one of the main integrating mechanisms of body function, closely tying somatic and visceral organs together to achieve integrated function.</p>,<p>In general, sympathetic control from the brain is often localised to specific visceral organs, suggesting that the brain, through the sympathetic nervous system, can selectively influence specific organ function.</p>,<p>Manipulative treatment of somatic structures can influence sympathetic function and hence visceral function through the somato-visceral reflex networks.</p>,<p>Sensitisation is a process that occurs in spinal grey matter (these are the interneurons which make the connection between the visceral and somatic structures) and results in an increased excitability of the involved neurons, thus increasing the gain of the input pathway.</p>,<p>Long term sensitisation is a longer lasting form of excitability increase in the reflex pathways that can last for hours and often occurs with the same stimuli as sensitisation.</p>,<p>Presumably permanent changes of reflex excitably can occur in reflex pathways with inhibitory cell death and new synapse formation.</p>,<p>Neurons exhibit a continual flow of intra axonal substances both away from and toward the cell body. This flow has been shown to include transport of proteins across the synapse from nerve cell to nerve cell and from nerve cell to end organ. Axonal transport.</p>,<p>The reflex system is a complex integrating network (remember the body is a unit). An important factor for the osteopath is the fact that somatic input can and does influence visceral function in the same way that afferent input from the viscera causes changes in the output to the somatic structures. Littlejohn said “disease always starts on the sensory side” so with this in mind it is difficult to think of many problems that don’t. This is important to us as osteopaths, we have to remember we are in the game of providing afferentation to create an opportunity for physiological change.</p>,<p>Manipulation of the somatic structures can alter the function of visceral structures through the same pathways. The reflexes are not simple systems with local influences, but interconnected that receive input from many sources and process that information for both local and distant areas of the body.</p>,<p>For normal function of the visceral and somatic systems, fluid movement and other body activities, complex and interacting networks must act harmoniously, so treatment has to be integrative, bringing the body together as a unit rather than treated as separate components. Again the principle “the body is a unit” and integration.</p>,<p>This means the lesion is not just a boney articular derangement but causes aberrant sensory afferentation into the dorsal horn of the spinal cord causing sensitisation, but also has an ascending affect through the sensory tracts and areas of these may become sensitised too. The afferent stimulus continues up to the brainstem where sensitisation can occur through the brainstem nuclei, reticular activating system, thalamus, hypothalamus, limbic system and cortical areas which can also become sensitised.</p>,<p>These areas are what are viewed on functional MRI, areas of large calibre fibres that are heavily myelinated and postulated as the cause of symptoms, but they are influenced and sensitised by ascending structures, they have to have sensory input to be affected and do not react on their own under their own volition.</p>,<p>From here there is a descending response influencing the activity of both somatic visceral and endocrine pathways. In many of the reflexes driven by visceral and somatic input, there is a strong effect by descending pathways on the lasting excitability of the reflex outflow. These descending influences can maintain the reflex outflow for extended periods. This may explain some of the long term increases in sensitivity, muscle contractions, and hyper excitable sympathetic output seen especially with visceral disturbances. Likewise, the long lasting descending influences can be inhibitory, resulting in lowered autonomic outflow. A bit like stocks and shares really they can go up or down.</p>,<p>Somatic stimulation can result in visceral inhibition. For example, the results of rib raising techniques, which is somatic stimulation, on sympathetic outflow which appears to be primarily inhibitory through the descending brain influences, resulting in decreased vasoconstriction and better fluid flow in the thoracic region.</p>,<p>Sensitisation phenomena suggests that maximal effectiveness of therapeutic procedures involving somatic afferent input to influence autonomic control may require frequent repetitions of the procedure to allow the response to build to its maximum.</p>,<p>So for normal function of viscera, muscles, fluid motion and other body activity, these complex and interacting networks within the nervous system must act together in concert.</p>,<p>Because the neurons involved in the increased excitability state are the interneurons of the grey matter, the neurons on which a variety of different pathways synapse, the data also supports the effects of excitability changes on both somatic and autonomic outflow because the inputs from both visceral and somatic structures end on common interneurons. When the excitability of the interneurons is altered the outflow to all structures, such as the vasomotors, from those interneurons is affected.</p>,<p>When the spinal cord becomes sensitised or facilitated and relays nociceptive signals to the brainstem where other reflexes concerning the autonomic nervous system and endocrine system may be initiated. It does not necessarily lead to the sensation of pain. These events can occur without conscious awareness of the situation. Projections from the spinal cord and trigeminal brainstem nuclei also reach the thalamus and activate thalamocorticol circuitry generating a network of activity on the cerebral cortex. Stressful stimulus will take the path of least resistance through these structures, that path often is an autonomic route, as described in this case.</p>,<p>Case history</p>,<p>67 year old female presenting with right elbow pain, during the consultation it became apparent that since giving birth to her second child some 30 odd years earlier she had been suffering from some bladder problems, for some years she been unable to run short distances without having stress incontinence and nocturia 6 times per night for which she is medicated with Vesicare which is a medication which essentially reduces the contraction of smooth muscle. In diagnosis its often useful to know what a medication is trying to achieve, most try to increase or decrease an action of the autonomic nervous system.</p>,<p>Examination of her spine revealed lesioning in her upper lumbar area at D12-L1-L2, this was part of a pattern of lesioning from her pelvis through her whole structure, but there was a lot of strain occurring at L1 due to the abrupt change of direction at this level putting increased strain at this segment and facilitation or sensitisation of the dorsal horn.</p>,<p>By activating autonomic structures via the interneurons of the dorsal horn this sends impulses up to the higher centres to the thalamus and cerebrum and a response is made which is relayed back down through the CNS to the visceral structure which responds according to the information provided, in this case smooth muscle contraction.</p>,<p>The lesion is not just a boney articular derangement but the tip of the iceberg causing aberrant sensory afferentation into the dorsal horn of the spinal cord resulting in sensitisation, this has an ascending affect through the sensory tracts and areas of these may become sensitised too. The afferent stimulus continues up to the brainstem where sensitisation can occur through the reticular activating system, thalamus, hypothalamus, limbic system and cerebrum.</p>,<p>This can increase the arousal state and push the person further along the adaptive pathway.</p>,<p>This is what is viewed on functional MRI, areas that are highly myelinated neurons and are postulated as the cause of symptoms, but they are influenced and sensitised by ascending structures, they have to have sensory input to be affected and do not react on their own under their own volition as isolated events.</p>,<p>From here there is a descending response influencing the activity of both somatic and visceral pathways. In this case the reflexes appear to be driven by the somatic tissues in the upper lumbar spine, there can be a strong effect by descending pathways on the lasting excitability of the reflex outflow. These descending influences can maintain this reflex outflow for extended periods.</p>,<p>The point here being that the lesion does not just cause a facilitated segment, but the whole reflex mechanisms involved are sensitised, this can include the ascending tracts, higher brain centres, descending tracts and peripheral sympathetics to the urinary bladder, it’s just not just a facilitated segment its a facilitated nervous system.</p>,<p>The patients nocturia reduced to 2 times per night after 3 treatments, she could run without wetting herself, and her tennis elbow pain of 6 months almost gone after 4 treatments.</p>,<img src="https://the-grid-user-content.s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/0bd2da2a-0fe3-4985-ab39-cf7538b113b7.jpg">,<p>Any questions?</p>,<p>Areas pain caused by heat is seen on fMRI are; The pattern included the thalamus, the posterior and anterior insula, the secondary somatosensory cortex, the anterior cingulate cortex, the periaqueductal gray matter, and other regions.</p>,<p>from NEJM.</p>,<p>An fMRI-Based Neurologic Signature of Physical Pain</p>,<p>Tor D. Wager, Ph.D., Lauren Y. Atlas, Ph.D., Martin A. Lindquist, Ph.D., Mathieu Roy, Ph.D., Choong-Wan Woo, M.A., and Ethan Kross, Ph.D.</p>,<p>N Engl J Med 2013; 368:1388-1397April 11, 2013DOI: 10.1056/NEJMoa1204471</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://thegrid.ai/osteopathichistory/kirksville-1898-south-west-quarter/index.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">5eab808a-d341-4357-8790-24d19421e351</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 22:56:10 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>